<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>RSE at Sheffield</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/</link><description>RSE at Sheffield</description><atom:link href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/rss.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 08:04:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>9 steps for quality research software</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/9_steps/</link><dc:creator>Mike Croucher</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I attended the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.software.ac.uk/"&gt;Software Sustainability Institute's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.software.ac.uk/cw16"&gt;Collaborations Workshop&lt;/a&gt; last month. This annual workshop is one of the primary events in the Research Software Engineering calendar and I highly recommend going to one if you are involved in the development of research software in any way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I worked on was a collaborative blog post called &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.software.ac.uk/blog/2016-04-05-9-steps-quality-research-software"&gt;9 steps for quality research software&lt;/a&gt;.  I also wrote an article about some of the work I do called &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.walkingrandomly.com/?p=5997"&gt;The accident and emergency of Research Software Engineering.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/9_steps/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 07:54:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sheffield RSE team collaborates with lecturers to teach computation</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/jupyter-for-chem-eng/</link><dc:creator>Mike Croucher</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img alt="/images/jupyter.png" src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/jupyter.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, I worked with Dr Marta Milo of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/bms"&gt;Department of Biomedical Science&lt;/a&gt; to develop a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://opendsi.cc/bioinformatics/"&gt;new course that taught the basics of Bioinformatics&lt;/a&gt; to biology undergraduates. Marta took care of the subject matter while I took care of getting it all to work in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jupyter.org/"&gt;Jupyter Notebook&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://cloud.sagemath.com/"&gt;Sage Math Cloud&lt;/a&gt;. I also gave crash courses in Jupyter, git and SageMathCloud to support staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course was a great success and demonstrated what can be achieved when academics partner with Research Software Engineers to deliver top quality computational teaching. My favourite comment from student feedback was &lt;strong&gt;The hardest thing ever, stressful, frustrating but very rewarding.&lt;/strong&gt; -- welcome to my life!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This success has led to me being invited to departmental teaching away days for subject areas that include a lot of computation in their syllabus. The most recent of these was with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/cbe"&gt;Department of chemical and biological engineering&lt;/a&gt;. I only had ten minutes but managed to include an introduction to the Sheffield RSE group, a quick demonstration of the Jupyter notebook, a discussion of the benefits of using SageMathCloud instead of the local managed desktop and the possibilities offered by this combination of technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, it's useful to be able to talk quickly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other discussions in the session I was involved with included a fantastic overview of flipped classroom teaching by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/cbe/staff/academic/spatwardhan"&gt;Siddharth Patwardhan&lt;/a&gt; and some of the upcoming challenges and opportunities in the higher education teaching sector by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/staff/news/pvc-learning-teaching-wyn-morgan-1.453796"&gt;Wyn Morgan&lt;/a&gt;, Sheffield's Pro-Vice-Chancellor for Learning and Teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Channeling my inner Ferris Beuller, &lt;strong&gt;The world of research software moves pretty fast. If you don't stop and look around for a while, you could miss it&lt;/strong&gt;. It was a pleasure to show off some of my favourite technology to the chemical and biological engineers and I look forward to working with them all in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slides from my talk are available at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mikecroucher.github.io/ChemEng_Jupyter_talk2016/"&gt;http://mikecroucher.github.io/ChemEng_Jupyter_talk2016/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/jupyter-for-chem-eng/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 07:26:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Windows 10 to support Linux binaries</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/linux-in-windows10-announce/</link><dc:creator>Ian Cottam</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The big news from Microsoft is that, from this summer, Windows 10 will
support user-mode programs from the popular Ubuntu Linux distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By "user-mode" we mean non-kernel things or, in other words, anything you
can type into a Bash shell command window. This is complete binary
compatibility: you can, for example, apt-get your favourite Linux tool or
just copy it over from an Ubuntu Linux system and it will run (assuming
you have any libraries it needs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The underlying technology is a new Windows' service that dynamically maps
Linux system calls to Windows ones, whilst maintaining the Linux
semantics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a big step for several reasons; here are just some:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;researchers who currently dual boot their laptops/desktops may not need
to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;researchers who run either Linux or Windows in a virtual machine may not
need to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;staff and students who buy expensive MacBooks mainly for its Unix
sub-system could buy a cheaper Windows 10 based laptop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as Windows 10 will be binary compatible with Linux it could be said to
have an advantage over Apple Macs which use the BSD version of Unix (as
BSD has numerous, small but sometimes annoying, differences to the tools found on
Linux)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it makes the path from developing on a laptop to a high-performance
computing cluster much more straightforward (i.e. basically the same Linux
toolset all the way)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new researchers attending software/data carpentry courses - to learn the
basics of good software engineering - will no longer have to work in a
system alien to their day-to-day computing environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm sure you can think of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devil is always in the details, but from reports to-date this is good news for researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mike Croucher, one of Sheffield's RSE Fellows, writes about the announcement on his blog: &lt;a href="http://www.walkingrandomly.com/?p=6011"&gt;http://www.walkingrandomly.com/?p=6011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lots more detail from Microsoft's Scott Hanselman &lt;a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/DevelopersCanRunBashShellAndUsermodeUbuntuLinuxBinariesOnWindows10.aspx"&gt;http://www.hanselman.com/blog/DevelopersCanRunBashShellAndUsermodeUbuntuLinuxBinariesOnWindows10.aspx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/linux-in-windows10-announce/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 10:25:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Our first Code Cafe: First steps with R</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/code-cafe-R/</link><dc:creator>Mike Croucher</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;We ran a 'Code Cafe' event for Coffee Revolution for Researchers who wanted to take their first steps with R. Details and class materials are at &lt;a href="http://www.walkingrandomly.com/?p=5981"&gt;http://www.walkingrandomly.com/?p=5981&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="R Code Cafe" src="http://www.walkingrandomly.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/CdIBvyEW8AAIUAA.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/code-cafe-R/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 19:06:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Open Astronomy / Software Carpentry Workshop</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/openastronomy-workshop/</link><dc:creator>Stuart Mumford</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week (11-15th January 2016) saw the first Open Astronomy workshop held at The University of Sheffield for the UK astronomy and solar physics communities. The first two days of the &lt;a href="http://openastronomy.org/2016-01-11-Sheffield/"&gt;workshop&lt;/a&gt; consisted of the core syllabus of &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;, covering git, bash and an introduction to programming with Python. The last three days provided an introduction to carrying out research in astronomy using Python. The attendees were mostly PhD students in Astrophysics from the University of Sheffield, however there were also representation of other fields (mathematics, medicine, ecology), from other universities (St. Andrews, Reading) and at different stages in their careers (post-docs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/openastronomy_workshop.jpg" alt="David teaching bash" align="right" width="40%"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop was taught by four different instructors (&lt;a href="https://github.com/CyclingNinja"&gt;Sam&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/drewleonard42"&gt;Drew&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/cadair"&gt;Stuart&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/dpshelio"&gt;David&lt;/a&gt;) with the help of &lt;a href="https://github.com/astrofrog/"&gt;Tom&lt;/a&gt; (an Astropy developer) on Thursday.
We all brought different expertise and shared the teaching out to keep the workshop lively over a gruelling five days none of us taught more than three hours in one go, and we alternated days between teaching and assisting.
We used the red-green post-it technique suggested by software carpentry as a way to know how people were getting on during the sessions, also, for every session the learners were asked to use these post-it notes to give us feedback on the session (green for something good you've learnt, red for something that can be improved).
This not just helped us for the next workshop, but it also helped to the next instructor that day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual there were some software setup issues at the beginning of the week, however we were very close!
Only one person from the whole class had trouble with the Jupyter notebook - it simply was not able to execute any command within. We didn't manage to fix the problem, but probably it was the oldest laptop (running Windows 7) in the class.
Beside that case, we come across a couple of other problems with other windows machines, in one of them &lt;code&gt;git log&lt;/code&gt; was blocking the screen and the other could not open the text editor (Notepad++ in this case) when executing &lt;code&gt;commit&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;merge&lt;/code&gt; with the default message).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each day we updated the &lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenAstronomy/2016-01-11_Sheffield_Notes"&gt;official repository&lt;/a&gt; with lesson templates in Jupyter notebook format, where an outline of the class was available, and the code cells were empty to be filled in while following the lecture. Once we completed a session, the notes can be browsed &lt;a href="http://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/OpenAstronomy/2016-01-11_Sheffield_Notes/blob/master/index.ipynb"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
In this way everyone had to &lt;code&gt;fork&lt;/code&gt; our repository on github, then &lt;code&gt;pull&lt;/code&gt; at the start of every session from &lt;code&gt;upstream&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;push&lt;/code&gt; at the end to their &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt;.
This cemented the work at the start of the week on git+GitHub, while making sure everyone had a backup of all the work they had completed during the week and learning the usual git workflow of contributing to a larger project on GitHub.
Thanks to the visualisations on GitHub we can see how all &lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenAstronomy/2016-01-11_Sheffield_Notes/network"&gt;these forks evolved&lt;/a&gt;, and see if the participants keep using GitHub!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During one of the sessions we discovered a bug in the latest release of SunPy. We used the opportunity to demonstrate what to do in these cases: fill an issue on GitHub and provide the information needed so the developers can replicate such error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be looking to repeat this workshop later in the year, probably before term starts in late September. In the meantime, feel free to use our material and contact us if you want more information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/openastronomy-workshop/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2016 12:15:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Building Capability and Support in Research Software</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/building-capability-and-support-in-research-software/</link><dc:creator>Mike Croucher</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I'll be starting my 5 year EPSRC Research Software Engineering fellowship in March 2016. For more details of the program of work, head over to my blog, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.walkingrandomly.com/?p=5948"&gt;http://www.walkingrandomly.com/?p=5948&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/building-capability-and-support-in-research-software/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2016 19:23:30 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>