<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>RSE at Sheffield (Mike Croucher)</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/authors/mike-croucher.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 08:20:27 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Sheffield RSE team supports lecturers in developing innovative undergraduate course material</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/jupyter-for-chem-eng/</link><dc:creator>Mike Croucher</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img alt="/images/jupyter.png" src="http://rse.shef.ac.uk/images/jupyter.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, I worked with Dr Marta Milo of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/bms"&gt;Department of Biomedical Science&lt;/a&gt; to develop a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://opendsi.cc/bioinformatics/"&gt;new course that taught the basics of Bioinformatics&lt;/a&gt; to biology undergraduates. Marta took care of the subject matter while I took care of getting it all to work in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jupyter.org/"&gt;Jupyter Notebook&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://cloud.sagemath.com/"&gt;Sage Math Cloud&lt;/a&gt;. I also gave crash courses in Jupyter, git and SageMathCloud to support staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course was a great success and demonstrated what can be achieved when academics partner with Research Software Engineers to deliver top quality computational teaching. My favourite comment from student feedback was &lt;strong&gt;The hardest thing ever, stressful, frustrating but very rewarding.&lt;/strong&gt; -- welcome to my life!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This success has led to me being invited to departmental teaching away days for subject areas that include a lot of computation in their syllabus. The most recent of these was with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/cbe"&gt;Department of chemical and biological engineering&lt;/a&gt;. I only had ten minutes but managed to include an introduction to the Sheffield RSE group, a quick demonstration of the Jupyter notebook, a discussion of the benefits of using SageMathCloud instead of the local managed desktop and the possibilities offered by this combination of technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, it's useful to be able to talk quickly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other discussions in the session I was involved with included a fantastic overview of flipped classroom teaching by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/cbe/staff/academic/spatwardhan"&gt;Siddharth Patwardhan&lt;/a&gt; and some of the upcoming challenges and opportunities in the higher education teaching sector by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/staff/news/pvc-learning-teaching-wyn-morgan-1.453796"&gt;Wyn Morgan&lt;/a&gt;, Sheffield's Pro-Vice-Chancellor for Learning and Teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Channeling my inner Ferris Beuller, &lt;strong&gt;The world of research software moves pretty fast. If you don't stop and look around for a while, you could miss it&lt;/strong&gt;. It was a pleasure to show off some of my favourite technology to the chemical and biological engineers and I look forward to working with them all in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slides from my talk are available at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mikecroucher.github.io/ChemEng_Jupyter_talk2016/"&gt;http://mikecroucher.github.io/ChemEng_Jupyter_talk2016/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/jupyter-for-chem-eng/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 07:26:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Our first Code Cafe: First steps with R</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/code-cafe-R/</link><dc:creator>Mike Croucher</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;We ran a 'Code Cafe' event for Coffee Revolution for Researchers who wanted to take their first steps with R. Details and class materials are at &lt;a href="http://www.walkingrandomly.com/?p=5981"&gt;http://www.walkingrandomly.com/?p=5981&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="R Code Cafe" src="http://www.walkingrandomly.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/CdIBvyEW8AAIUAA.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/code-cafe-R/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 19:06:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Building Capability and Support in Research Software</title><link>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/building-capability-and-support-in-research-software/</link><dc:creator>Mike Croucher</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I'll be starting my 5 year EPSRC Research Software Engineering fellowship in March 2016. For more details of the program of work, head over to my blog, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.walkingrandomly.com/?p=5948"&gt;http://www.walkingrandomly.com/?p=5948&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>http://rse.shef.ac.uk/blog/building-capability-and-support-in-research-software/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2016 19:23:30 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>